A Guide to the Iris Alex Collection 1956-2002
Digital Library and Archive, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Digital Library and Archives, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Iris Alex Collection 1956-2002
Digital Library and Archive, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Va.
Ms2002-026
1 container (1 document box); .5 cu. ft.
Development Administrator for Facilities Development Corporation of the State of New York, building consultant for the Young Women's Christian Association, and Fellow of the American Institute of Architects. Active from the 1950s until 1991. The collection includes both volumes of A Building Manual for the YWCA, written by Alex as well as some biographical information and articles about her work. Also contains correspondence between Alex and other architects about Julia Morgan.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
The Iris Alex Collection was donated to the International Archives of Women in Architecture at the Digital Library and Archives by their creator in 2000, with two additional donations in 2002.
Biographical/Historical Information
Architect Iris S. Alex (b. 1926) studied at the Institute of Design at the Illinois Institute of Technology. She spent 13 years working for the architectural firm of Skidmore, Owings and Merrill. In the 1970s, Alex worked part-time at Related Designs, Inc. Her main employment was with the National Board of the Young Women's Christian Association where she served as the National Architect starting in 1970. While with the YWCA, she developed and oversaw its building advisory service and wrote a two-volume Building Manual for the YWCA. In 1981 she began working as the Development Administrator for Facilities Development Corporation of the State of New York, a position she held until her retirement in 1991.
Scope and Content
The Iris Alex Collection contains material about Alex's career, including a resume, magazine articles, blueprints and a two-volume building manual. It also contains her correspondence with other architects about the career of architect Julia Morgan. There is also correspondence with Morgan's biographer, Sara Boutelle.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into two series, one containing information about Iris Alex's professional career, and one containing information that Alex collected about architect Julia Morgan.
Series I includes a resume, copies of three building plans, articles and photographs showing projects Alex worked on, and both volumes of the YWCA building handbook that she wrote.
Series II consists of clippings about Julia Morgan, correspondence with other architects and historians about Morgan's work, and correspondence with Morgan's biographer, Sara Boutelle.
Contents List
- Professional Information, 1959-2002
  - Biographical Information, 1998-2002 (Box-folder 1-1)
  - Plan for a House Addition, 1959 (Box-folder 1-2)
  - Blueprints for a Skidmore, Owings and Merrill Project, 1962 (Box-folder 1-3)
  - Article and Photographs about Bassett Hospital Project in Cooperstown, NY for Skidmore, Owings and Merrill, 1968-1971 (Box-folder 1-4)
  - Articles on Projects for Related Designs, 1972-1974 (Box-folder 1-5)
  - A Building Manual for the YWCA, Volumes 1 and 2, by Iris Alex, 1978, 1981 (Box-folder 1-6)
  - Correspondence About Work for the State of New York Facilities Development Corporation, 1981-1992 (Box-folder 1-7)
- Julia Morgan Information 1976-1991
  - Clippings and Photographs of Julia Morgan and Her Work, 1976-1988 (Box-folder 1-8)
  - Correspondence About Julia Morgan, 1976-1981 (Box-folder 1-9)
  - Correspondence About Julia Morgan with Sara Boutelle, 1976-1991 (Box-folder 1-10)
  - Information about Sara Boutelle, 1990 (Box-folder 1-11)